Berkshire and Columbia Missionary Society records, 1798-2002.
Congregational Library Archives
Berkshire and Columbia Missionary Society records, 1798-2002.
RG4696
Congregational Library Archives
.97 Cubic Feet
(3 boxes)
The Berkshire and Columbia Missionary Foundation was a missionary society that was officially founded in February 1798. It is considered to be the oldest missionary society in the US, predating the "Haystack Movement" by eight years. The year prior, members met at the Green River in Hillsdale, N.Y. where it was suggested that a group form to send out missionaries both far and near. The locations that they decided upon included parts of Vermont, Ohio, Pennsylvania, Massachusetts and New Hampshire. By 1810, the movement has ten missionaries who gave out tracts and bibles to help the areas determined to be "destitute settlements". In the two centuries that followed, the foundation donated funds to over 100 different organizations and individuals. The organizations officially closed its doors in 2002. This collection contains meeting and secretary notes, financial information, newspaper clippings, histories, correspondences and programs.
Beckwith, Kenneth Daggett, 1896-
Berkshire and Columbia Missionary Society
Boynton, Nehemiah
Nettleton, Albert
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Received in 2003; 2003-12.
Historical Information
The Berkshire and Columbia Missionary Foundation was a missionary society that was officially founded in February 1798. It is considered to be the oldest missionary society in the US, predating the "Haystack Movement" by eight years. The year prior, members met at the Green River in Hillsdale, N.Y. where it was suggested that a group form to send out missionaries both far and near. The locations that they decided upon included parts of Vermont, Ohio, Pennsylvania, Massachusetts and New Hampshire. By 1810, the movement has ten missionaries who gave out tracts and bibles to help the areas determined to be "destitute settlements". In the two centuries that followed, the foundation donated funds to over 100 different organizations and individuals. The organizations officially closed its doors in 2002.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains meeting and secretary notes, financial information, newspaper clippings, histories, correspondences and programs.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 5 series and each one is further arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Meeting Minutes and Records, 1798-1998.
Series 2: Finances, 1798-2002.
Series 3: History, 1831-1982.
Series 4: Correspondences, 1853-2002.
Series 5: Programs, 1962-1963, undated.
Bibliography
Berkshire and Columbia Missionary Society. Oldest Missionary Society in the United States. Massachusetts, n.d.
Missionary societies.; Missionaries -- Correspondence, reminiscences, etc.; Church finance.; Beckwith, Kenneth Daggett, 1896-; Berkshire and Columbia Missionary Society; Boynton, Nehemiah; Nettleton, Albert
- Meeting minutes and records, 1798 1998; 1798-1998; 9 Items; (7 folders, 2 volumes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains meeting minutes, secretary notes, member lists and the constitution for the Berkshire and Columbia Missionary Society.
  - Meeting records, 1798 1817; 1798-1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitution with copies, 1798 1961; 1798, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Meeting records, 1819 1853; 1819-1853 (Box 3, Volume 3)
  - Meeting records, 1827 1853; 1827-1853 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Secretary records, 1858 1928; 1858-1928 (Box 3, Volume 4)
  - Meeting records, 1947 1983; 1947, 1963-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Meeting records, 1948 1951; 1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Meeting records, 1984 2002; 1984-2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Membership lists, 1990 1998; 1990, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Finances, 1798 2002; 1798-2002; 15 Cubic Feet; (13 folders, 2 volumes)
  This series contains financial information for the Berkshire and Columbia Missionary Society, including treasury records, contributions, transfer of stewardship, tax and bank information and canceled bankbooks.
  - Financial records, 1798 1835; 1798-1835 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Treasury records, 1825 1948; 1825-1948 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Financial information, 1834 1852; 1834, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Financial information, 1901 1919; 1901-1919 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Financial information, 1912 1917; 1912-1917 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Financial information, 1918 1929; 1918-1929 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Financial information, 1932 1939; 1932-1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Financial information, 1940 1949; 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Contributions and donations, 1961 1993; 1961-1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Financial information, 1966 1972; 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Tax and bank information, 1970 1995; 1970-1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Financial information, 1981 1989; 1981-1989 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Financial information, 1990 2002; 1990-2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Transfer of stewardship, 2001 2002; 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Canceled bankbooks, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- History, 1831 1982; 1831-1982; 10 Folders
  This series contains historical information related to the Berkshire and Columbia Missionary Society, such as newspaper clippings, maps, scrapbook pieces anda history of the society.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1831 1839; 1831-1839 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Histories, 1934 1961; 1934, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook pieces, 1946 1962; 1946-1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook pieces, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1963 1982; 1963-1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - History of the Society, 1798-1961 (original), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - History of the Society, 1798-1961 (copy), undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Historical maps, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - History pamphlet, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sample of letterhead and envelope, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1853 2002; 1853-2002; 8 Folders
  This series contains correspondences of the Berkshire and Columbia Missionary Society, including those of Albert Nettleton, Kenneth Beckwith, Nehemiah Boynton and more.
  - Correspondence, 1853, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1916 1919; 1916-1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with Albert Nettleton, 1951 1965; 1951-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with Kenneth Beckwith, 1951 1968; 1951-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with Nehemiah Boynton, 1955 1966; 1955-1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1960 1972; 1960-1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1980 1998; 1980-1998 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 2001 2002; 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Programs, 1962 1963; 1962-1963, undated; 2 Folders
  This series contains information on the Mission to America and Helping Migrants programs.
  - Mission to America, 1962 1963; 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Helping Migrants program, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)